Guide to the Records of the New York Exchange for Woman's Work 1878-2003 MS 446
New-York Historical Society
New York Exchange for Women's Work
1878-2003
New-York Historical Society
MS 446
7.25 Linear feet (18 boxes and 3 volumes)
The collection consists of the records of the New York Exchange for Woman's Work, a charitable institution whose mission was to provide a retail outlet for the handiwork of needy consignors. The records include board minutes, corporate, financial, and real estate papers, advertising materials, clippings, photographs, and ephemera.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Biographical Note
Missing Title
1878 In March, the New York Exchange for Woman's Work is founded by Mrs. William G. Choate, Candace Wheeler, and approximately 20 other women, with Mrs. Choate as President. Thirty articles are offered for sale in Mrs. Choate's home at 108 East 31st Street. Within a month, the Exchange moves to larger quarters at 4 East 20th Street. In November, the Exchange is incorporated in New York State.
1894 The Exchange moves to 329 Fifth Avenue, and publishes its first catalogue.
1899 The Exchange moves to 334 Madison Avenue, and opens its first lunch counter.
1915 The Exchange opens the Vocational Bureau. This division places women in positions as domestic and office workers.
1917 Mrs. John Seely Ward becomes President of the Exchange.
1919-1920 The Exchange purchases twin five-story houses at 539-541 Madison Avenue. Restaurant service is expanded on the ground floor, and the shop occupies the second floor. Additional space is used for offices and for the Exchange's other activities, including the Vocational Bureau. The Exchange also provides training services, teaching women skills such as dressmaking.
1934 Mrs. Robert C. Ream becomes President of the Exchange. Amid letters of protest and extensive media coverage, the "Crinoline Bar" opens in the Exchange Restaurant. Also this year, the Federation of Woman's Exchanges is founded.
1936 The first Exchange Revue is published.
1966 Mrs. Fergus Reid, Jr. becomes President of the Exchange.
1969 Mrs. William J. Lippincott becomes President of the Exchange.
1970s The Internal Revenue Service begins to question the tax-exempt status of the Exchange's Restaurant. Proceeds from the Restaurant have traditionally been used to offset loses from the consignment shop. The IRS concludes that Restaurant itself does not serve the Exchange's charitable mission, and must become a for-profit establishment.
1979-1980 The property at 539-541 Madison Avenue is sold to real estate developers; the Exchange moves to 660 Madison Avenue. Although the salesroom is reopened, the Restaurant is permanently closed.
1984 Mrs. Richard E. Metz becomes President of the Exchange.
1986 Mrs. Bromwell Ault becomes President of the Exchange.
1988 Mrs. A. Reading Van Doren, Jr. becomes President of the Exchange.
1990-1991 The Exchange moves to 1095 Third Avenue.
1997 The Exchange moves to 149 East 60th Street.
2003 Unable to raise enough money to meet growing expenses, the Exchange closes in February.
Scope and Content Note
The records of the New York Exchange for Woman's Work include board minutes, corporate, financial, and real estate papers, advertising materials, clippings, photographs, video and ephemera. The New York Exchange was one of many such organizations founded in the late nineteenth century. Its original aim was to help "gentlewomen in reduced circumstances" principally Civil War widows) achieve economic independence. The Exchange sold the handiwork of these women, including crafts, giftware, decorative items, clothing, pickles, preserves, and baked goods. Over the course of the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, the organization grew to include an employment agency, a vacation home where needy women were hosted free of charge, training and education facilities, and a Restaurant and Bar. Over time the Exchange also began to accept work from needy women (and, by the 1970s, men) of all social classes.
The collection supports research on the history of philanthropy, women's employment, and women's exchanges (which at one time numbered over 70 in the United States and Canada). The collection contains materials related to the corporate history of the Exchange, including nearly complete minutes of monthly and annual meetings of the Board of Directors (variously referred to as Board of Managers) and various subcommittees. The minutes detail the challenges of running a not-for-profit business, and provide insight into the social changes which occurred over the course of the twentieth century, particularly in regard to employment opportunities for women. Because it moved nine times in the course of its 125-year history, the collection also contains a great deal of material related to the real estate owned and rented by the Exchange.
For many years the Exchange was just as well-known for its Restaurant as for its shop. The collection includes menus, recipes, and cookbooks from the Restaurant, as well as numerous newspaper and magazine articles which comment on the experience of dining at the Exchange. Also of interest are the publications produced by the Exchange. In particular, the Exchange Revue, a magazine/catalog first published in 1936 contains articles on the subjects of fashion and beauty, housekeeping, entertaining, home decorating, literature, film, and theater, in addition to advertisements for local businesses and news about the Exchange.
The collection also contains materials related to public relations efforts of the Exchange. Press releases and PR strategies mainly date from the 1990s, but newspaper clippings and advertisements have been preserved from as early as 1919.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into the following thirteen series:
Missing Title
Series I. Minutes, 1878-1997
Series II. Corporate Documents, 1878-1987, n.d.
Series III. Financial Documents, 1911-1997, n.d.
Series IV. Real Estate Documents, 1914-2000
Series V. Correspondence, 1878-2003, n.d.
Series VI. Menus and Recipes, 1937-1980, n.d.
Series VII. Publications, 1894-1994, n.d.
Series VIII. Advertising and Public Relations Materials, 1918-2002
Series IX. Fundraising, 1879-2000, n.d.
Series X. Photogrpahs and Video, 1981-1990, n.d.
Series XI. Historical Information, 1891-1998, n.d.
Series XII. Other Exchanges and the Federation of Woman's Exchanges, 1879-2000, n.d.
Series XIII. In-Store Displays and Exhibits, n.d.
The materials are arranged chronologically within each series.
Wills.; Video; Clippings (information artifacts); Catalogs (documents); Bank Books; Annual reports.; Account books.; Women's exchanges -- United States -- History.; Scrapbooks.; Women -- Employment -- United States -- History.; Restaurants.; Nonprofit Organizations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Cookery; Consignment sale shops; Charity Organization; Ephemera.; Insurance policies.; Leases.; Ledgers (account books); Magazines (periodicals).; Menus.; Minutes (administrative records); Pamphlets.; Press releases.; Tax records; Photographs.; Correspondence.; Van Doren, Manie (Mrs. A. Reading); Ward, Madeleine McLean (Mrs. John Seely); Wheeler, Candace, 1827-1923; Ault, Allie (Mrs. Bromwell); Choate, Mary Atwater; Federation of Woman's Exchanges; Lippincott, Aileen Sedgwick Taylor (Mrs. William J.); Metz, Gurdon (Mrs. Richard E.); New York Exchange for Woman's Work; Ream, Priscilla M. (Mrs. Robert C.); Reid, Etheldreda S. (Mrs. Fergus); Sander, Kathleen Waters
- Series I: Minutes,1878-1997
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains minutes of the monthly and annual meetings of the Board of Directors (also known as the Board of Managers) of the New York Exchange for Woman's Work. Also included are Annual Reports, minutes of subcommittees, and Annual Reports to the Federation of Woman's Exchanges.
  - Minutes, 1878, 1892-1893 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1901-1919 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Minutes (Copies and Related Materials), 1878-1921 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes (Copies and Related Materials), 1878-1921 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes (Copies and Related Materials), 1878-1921 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes (Copies and Related Materials), 1878-1921 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1930-1935 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1936-February 1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, March 1940-1943 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1944-February 1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, March 1948-September 1950 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, October 1950-February 1954 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, March 1954-December 1955 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1956-February 1954 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, March 1959-January 1961 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, February 1961-February 1964 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, March 1946-September 1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, November 1966-February 1970 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Minutes (Copies/Drafts), 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, March 1970-February 1974 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Minutes (Copies/Drafts), 1971-1974 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, March 1974-1978 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Minutes (Copies/Drafts), 1975-1978 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, May 1978-May 1986 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Minutes (Copies/Drafts), 1979-1984 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Minutes (Copies/Drafts), 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1987-1989 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 1992-1997 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Series II: Corporate Documents, 1887-1987, n.d.
  This series contains materials relating to the status of the Exchange as a not-for-profit corporation organized and existing under the laws of New York State.
  - Certificate of Incorporation (Copies), 1887 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Corporate Documents, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Stock Certificate Book, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Corporate Resolution, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - By-Laws, 1953, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Board Members - Biographical Information, 1927-1987, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Series III: Financial Documents, 1911-1997, n.d.
  This series contains financial records of the Exchange, including materials relating to investments, taxes, accounting, and inventory. The series is divided into six subseries.
  - Subseries 1: Investments and Bank Accounts,1911-1994
    This subseries contains materials relating to investment and bank accounts. Also included are financial statements and wills in which bequests to the Exchange were made.
    - Account Book-Building and Endowment Fund, 1911-1921 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Investments, 1911-1916, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Wills (Bequests to Exchange), 1919-1978 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Account Book, 1972-1994 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Bank Books, 1956-1981 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Financial Statements, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 2: Taxes, 1939-1997
    This subseries contains materials relating to the Exchange's tax-exempt status, as well as federal, state and local tax returns.
    - IRS Letters Re:Tax Exempt Status, 1939-1991 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence/Forms Re:Tax-Exempt Status, 1952-1986 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Tax Returns, 1977-1984 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Real Estate Taxes, 1979-1984 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Real Estate Taxes, 1992-1997 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 3: Consignor and Inventory Records, 1957-1988, n.d.
    This subseries contains account records of consignors, the Exchange's policies for consignors, inventory records, and order forms for purchased goods.
    - Consignor's Sundry Accounts (Volume [1])
    - Consignor Records, 1957-1989 (Box Unknown container 570 for instance of Consignor Records, Folder unknown container)
    - Consignor Records, 1963-1975 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Inventory Records, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Plum Pudding Works - Flyers and Orders, 1987-1988 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Facsimile of Printing Block for Consignor's Invoice, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Inventory Records, 1954-1989 (Box 15, Folder unknown container)
    - Printing Block for Consignor's Invoice, n.d. (Box 17, Folder unknown container)
  - Subseries 4: Accounting Records, 1938-1940
    This subseries contains records related to accounting, including materials related to a computerized bookkeeping system used by the organization in the 1980s.
    - Account Book, 1938-1940. (Volume [2])
    - Computerized Bookkeeping System, 1986-1988 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Petty Cash Slip, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Subseries 5: Merchant Deposit Cards, n.d.
    This subseries contains the cards used to make imprints on credit card receipts.
    - Merchant Deposit Summary Cards, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Subseries 6: Employment Records, 1922-1981, n.d.
    This subseries contains materials related to paid employees of the Exchange.
    - Employment, 1922-1981, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Series IV: Real Estate Documents, 1914-2000
  This series contains documents related to properties owned and leased by the Exchange. Included are mortgage agreements, leases, invoices for repairs, renovations, and rent, insurance policies, and related correspondence.
  - Real Estate Documents, 1914-1919 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Minutes of Meetings Re: Sale of 334 Madison Avenue, 1919 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Real Estate Documents, 1950-1934 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Real Estate Documents, 1935-1959 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Real Estate Documents, 1914-1919 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Real Estate Documents, 1970-1976 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Real Estate Documents, 1977-1978 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Real Estate Documents, January-May 1979 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Real Estate Documents, June-December 1979 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Real Estate Documents, January-March 1980 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Real Estate Documents, April-June 1980 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Real Estate Documents, July-December 1980 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Real Estate Documents, 1981-1990 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Real Estate Documents, 1991-1997 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Real Estate Documents, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Series V: Correspondence, 1878-2003
  This series contains letters written to and from the Board of Directors of the Exchange. Included are letters of resignation from Board members and staff, as well as letters from customers and donors. The materials are arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence, 1878-1973 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1981-2003, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Series VI: Menus and Recipes, 1934-1980, n.d.
  This series contains menus from the Exchange Restaurant, cookbooks published by the Exchange and by other philanthropic organizations, and collections of recipes.
  - Restaurant Menus, 1934-1980, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Cookbooks, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Recipe Scrapbook, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Recipe Cards, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Recipe Scrapbook (disbound) (Box 16, Folder 1)
- Series VII: Publications, 1894-1994, n.d.
  This series contains pamphlets and magazines published by the Exchange. Also included are materials which the staff used to generate ideas for issues of the Exchange Revue, and artwork which was used in the magazine.
  - Catalogue, 1894, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Catalogue, 1974-1923 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Catalogue, 1924-1926 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Yearbook, 1927-1929 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Yearbook, 1930-1934 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Exchange Revue, 1936-1937 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Exchange Revue, 1938 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Exchange Revue, 1939 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Exchange Revue, 1940 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Exchange Revue, 1941 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Exchange Revue, 1942 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Exchange Revue, 1970-1978 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Exchange Revue, 1979-1994 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Exchange Revue Ideas, 1953-1990 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Artwork for Exchange Revue, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Templates for Exchange Revue, Holiday 1990 (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Series VIII: Advertising and Public Relations, 1918-2002
  This series contains advertising and public relations materials, as well as clippings, promotional materials, and business-related ephemera. It is divided into four subseries.
  - Subseries 1: Advertisements, 1918-1998
    This subseries contains advertisements created by the Exchange. The earlier material (1918-1930) was originally placed in scrapbooks. These books have been disbound, but the materials remain in their original order. The later materials (1990-1998) consist of guidebooks and programs in which the Exchange placed advertisements.
    - Advertisements, 1918-1922 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Advertisements, 1922-1923 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Advertisements, 1924 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Advertisements, 1925 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Advertisements, 1925-1926 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Advertisements, 1927 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Advertisements, 1929-1930 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Advertisements, 1930 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - City Guide, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Blue Hill Troupe Programs, 1996-1998 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - New York Quick Guide, 1998 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 2: Relations Materials, 1990-2002
    This subseries contains press releases, public relations handbooks, and public relations recommendations. It also contains press books which were originally housed in binders. These press books contain primarily clippings, press releases, and promotional items. The materials have been removed from the binders, but the original order has been preserved..
    - Press Book, ca. 1990-1993 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Press Book, 1993-2002 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Press Book, 1993-2002 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Press Releases, 1986-1994 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Public Relations Recommendations, 1990-1995 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Public Relations Handbooks, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 3: Clippings, ca. 1920-1999, n.d.
    This subseries contains newspaper and magazine clippings. Also included are magazines which featured stories about the Exchange. The album, 1965-1978, has been disbound and rehoused in its original order in Box 18. A facsimile of the bound volume is available in Box 16.
    - Clippings, 1934 (Volume [3])
    - Album, 1965-1978 (Volume [4])
    - Clippings, 1953-1989 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Clippings, 1990-1999, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Town & Country Magazine, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - People Magazine, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Facsimile of disbound volume, 1965-1978 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Scrapbook, ca. 1920-1953 (Box 18, Folder 1-4)
  - Subseries 3: Promomotional Materials and Ephemera, 1988-1991, n.d.
    This subseries contains materials such as stationary, postcards, bookmarks, shopping bags, stickers, tissue paper, and business cards featuring the Exchange logo. Also included are materials related to the redesign of the Exchange logo in 1991, including artwork, order forms, invoices from printers, and a sign that hung outside the shop on East 60th Street.
    - Promotional Materials, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Logo, c1991 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Ephemera with New Logo, c1991 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Brochures, c1990s (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Business Materials/Ephemera, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Drawing, illustration, template for wrapping paper, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Display items, matted drawings, illustrations, 1991, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Plexiglass sign, n.d. (Box unboxed)
- Series IX: Fundraising, 1879-2000, n.d.
  This series contains materials relating to various fundraising activities of the Exchange, including the annual appeal and theater benefit, as well as in-store events.
  - Fundraising Appeals/Benefits, 1879-1936, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Appeals/Benefits, 1953-1991 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Appeal Expense Records, 1955-1960 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Appeal Letter Ideas, ca. 1990s (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Mailings to Supporters, 1981-2000 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Beatrix Potter Event, 1986-1988 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Guest Book, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Series X: Photographs and Video, 1981-1990, n.d.
  This series contains photographs of the interior and exterior of the Exchange shops, Restaurant, and offices at 539-541 Madison Avenue, 660 Madison Avenue, 1095 Third Avenue, and 149 East 60th Street. Many of the photographs depict the merchandise for sale at the Exchange. There are also photographs of board members, employees, and customers. In addition, there is a VHS cassette featuring a 1990 episode of "What It Takes," a local television program featuring the Executive Director of the Exchange, Catherine Dinehart.
  - Photographs, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Photographs (Proofs/Correspondence), 1981 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Beatrix Potter Photographs, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Photo Album, 1989 (Box 13)
  - Photo Album, n.d. (Box 13)
  - Video "What It Takes" T.V., 1990 (Box 13)
- Series XI: Historical Information, 1891-1998, n.d.
  This series contains information collected by the Exchange about its own historical development. It also includes a dissertation entitled "'Not A Lady Among Us': Entrepreneurial Philanthropy and Economic Independence as Expressed Through the Woman's Exchange Movement, 1832-1900," written by Kathleen Waters Sander on woman's exchanges in the United States (including the New York Exchange for Woman's Work), as well as correspondence relating to a book (The Business of Charity: The Woman's Exchange Movement, 1832-1900) written by Sander on the same topic.
  - "Not A Lady Among Us"/The Business of Charity, 1994-1998 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Historical Notes/Essays, 1891-1984, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Notes for Historical Brochure, 1990 (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Series XII: Other Exchanges and thw Federation of Woman's Exchanges, n.d.
  This series contains pamphlets created by other woman's exchanges, including the Peña-Peck House, the Baltimore Woman's Industrial Exchange, and the St. Louis Woman's Exchange. It also contains materials published by the Federation of Woman's Exchanges.
  - Other Exchanges/Federation, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Series XIII: In-Store Displays and Exhibits, 1879-2000, n.d.
  This series contains a number of matted photographs, advertisements, menus, and clippings which were used as part of an in-store exhibit, as well as framed photographs and other materials which were used to decorate the store.
  - Matted oversize clippings, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, ca. 1966, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Displays, 2000, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Matted pamphlets and clippings, menu, note, 1879-1992 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Matted ephemera, advertisements, clippings, invitations, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Photograph and document formerly adhered to Lippincott's plaque, 1981, 1986, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Documents removed from small picture frame, 1991, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Drawing, descriptive documents, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Misc. exhibit labels, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Color illustration of exhibit design "plaid stripes on columns and center" (rolled) (Box 16)
  - Color illustration of exhibit design (rolled), n.d. (Box 16)
  - Fabric swatches (in 2 rolls), n.d. (Box 16)
  - Plaque in appreciation of Mrs. William J. Lippincott, n.d. (Box 17)